Guide to the William Peirce Randel Papers, 1852-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Peirce Randel papers 1852-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Randel, William Peirce, 1909-
1.2 linear feet Extent: Approximately 735 Items
Historian and professor of English, University of Maine. Correspondence, addresses, proofs, drafts and reprints of articles, reviews, and photographs, all concerning William Peirce Randel's work on Edward Eggleston, a Methodist circuit rider who turned agnostic. Includes a bibliography of Randel's writings, and 23 photographs of Eggleston, his home, and various locations where he was active.
RL.01065
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, parts of this collection are minimally processed and may need further processing before they can be used.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Peirce Randel Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1986 and 1988.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, addresses, proofs, drafts and reprints of articles, reviews, and photographs, all concerning William Peirce Randel's work on Edward Eggleston, a Methodist circuit rider who turned agnostic and then became president of the American Historical Association. The papers in this collection relate to Randel's research and writings on Eggleston and include correspondence with Eggleston family members, research libraries, Twayne Publishers, King's Cross Publishers, his adviser Ralph L. Rusk, and with others who were doing or had done research on Eggleston. Included are Randel's 1945 dissertation, drafts of his 1963 Edward Eggleston: Hoosier Realist, two volumes of Scribner's Monthly Magazine for 1878, which contain the serialized story Roxy by Eggleston; an inventory of the Eggleston collection at Cornell University; and 23 photographs of Eggleston, his home, and locations where he was active.
Acquired as part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography at Duke University.
The collection is arranged in four series: Correspondence, Writings, Writings by Others, and Photographs.
Subject Headings
Cansler, Ronald L. (Robert Lee), 1947-; Eggleston, Edward, 1837-1902; Randel, William Peirce, 1909-; Agnosticism -- History -- 19th century; Circuit riders -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Methodist Church -- United States -- History; Scribner’s Monthly Magazine; Columbia University; Twayne Publishers; Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1852-1900, 1938-1982, (1 box)
  Contains correspondence with Eggleston family members, research libraries, Twayne Publishers, King's Cross Publishers, Randel's adviser Ralph L. Rusk, and with others who were doing or had done research on Eggleston. Also included are copies of Eggleston's correspondence from the 1800s, an inventory of the Eggleston collection at Cornell University, and correspondence concerning the Bibliography of American Literature.
  - General Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Geberal Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1960-1982 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, selected, 1936-1944 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography of American Literature, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Copies of Eggleston correspondence, 1852-1900 (Box 1)
  - Copyright, 1943, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Cornell University, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence about photographs, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - King's Cross Press, 1945-1948 (Box 3)
  - Twayne Publishers, 1961-1963, 1981 (Box 1)
- Writings Series, 1945-1967, (2 boxes)
  Among Randel's writings in this collection are drafts and proofs or articles and books on Eggleston, a copy of his dissertation on Eggleston completed at Columbia University in 1945, bibliographic and other notes, and an index to the most important Eggleston correspondents.
  - Article Drafts, 1959, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation: Edward Eggleston, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Drafts: Edward Eggleston: Hoosier Realist, 1963 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Drafts: The Circuit Rider, introduction by William Peirce Randel, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Other Writings, undated (Box 2)
  - Projected Writings for the Minnesota Historical Society and the University of Minnesota Press (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Proofs: Edward Eggleston, #45 in Twayne's United States Authors Series, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, 1945, 1953 (Box 2)
- Writings by Others Series, 1870-1878, 1937-1984, (1 box)
  This series contains proofs of The Circuit Rider, edited by Randel; reviews of Randel's book Edward Eggleston; a copy of Ronald Cansler's Ph.D. thesis entitled Edward Eggleston's 'An Agnostic': a Novel of the Soul; reprints by others; and two volumes of Scribner's Monthly Magazine for 1878, which contain the serialized story Roxy by Eggleston, which Randel edited for republication.
  - Edward Eggleston, Roxy, Schribner's Monthly (November 1877-February 1878) (Box 2)
  - Edward Eggleston's An Agnostic; A Novel of the Soul, Dissertation by Ronald L. Cansler, 1986 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Proofs: The Circuit Rider, by Edward Eggleston, edited and with introduction by William Peirce Randel, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Reprints by Others, 1937, 1945, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Reviews, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Writings about Eggleston by others (with some correspondence about them), 1964-1984 (Box 3)
  - Writings by unidentified others, 1870-1871 (Box 3)
- Photographs Series, undated, (1 box)
  Contains 23 photographs of Eggleston, his home and other sites in Indiana, Minnesota, and Virginia, his coat of arms, his estate in Lake George, New York, and his grave.
  - Photographs (Box 3)